<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King whereas wee haue euer since it pleased God to establish vs in the imperiall crowne of Great Britaine, equally equally regarded the good of both the late kingdomes of Scotland and England ...</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22016</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8377</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3684</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33150760</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33150760</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28743</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22016)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28743)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1875:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King whereas wee haue euer since it pleased God to establish vs in the imperiall crowne of Great Britaine, equally equally regarded the good of both the late kingdomes of Scotland and England ...</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker, Printer to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Countering rumours that the Church of Scotland will be required to conform to the Church of England.</note>
                  <note>Other title information from first 4 lines of text.</note>
                  <note>"Giuen at our Honour of Hampton Court the 26. day of September, in the third yeere of our Reigne of Great Britaine, France and Ireland."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:28743:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the King.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas wee haue ſine it pleaſed God to eſtabliſh vs in the Imperiall Crowne</hi> of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> equally regarded the good of both the late Kingdomes of Scotland and England, now happily vnited our Royal perſon in one Monarchie, euer minding to maintaine and continue the good and lowable cuſtomes and Lawes whereby each of them hath beene theſe many ages ſo worthily gouerned: neuertheleſſe ſome malitious ſpirits, enemies to that common tranquilitie ſo much deſired by vs (forgetting the many proofes both publique and priuate, which we haue giuen of that our gratious affection to that our natiue and ancient countrey of <hi>North Britaine,</hi> of the freedome, libertie and priuiledges whereof wee haue at all occaſions taken ſo ſpeciall a patrociny, as the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne aſſemblies of the Eſtates of <hi>South Britaine,</hi> and Commiſſioners from the Eſtates of both Kingdomes haue beene eye witneſſes) haue not beene aſhamed to labour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the mindes of our beſt affected ſubiects, That whereas the inſolent and factious carriage of ſome of them hath merited moſt ſeuere animaduerſion, they would inſinuate themſelues in the commiſeration of the multitude, by aſſuming vnto them a glorious profeſſion of the maintaining of the Priuiledges and auctorized diſcipline, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by vs (as they affirme) to be vtterly ouerthrowne by a ſudden and vnſeaſonable laying vpon them at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the Rites, Ceremonies, and whole Eccleſiaſticall order eſtabliſhed in the Church of this part of our Kingdome of <hi>Britaine.</hi> And as wee haue euer carefully regarded how conuenient it is to maintaine euery Countrey in that forme of gouernment which is fitteſt and can beſt agree with the conſtitution thereof, and how dangerous altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are without good aduice and mature deliberation, and that euen in matters of order of the Church, in ſome ſmall Ilands vnder our Dominions, we haue abſtained from ſuffering any alteration: So doubt we not, but our good Subiects will neuer be that credulous contrary to the knowne trueth, which hath euer appeared clearely in all our Actions, as to be in any doubt, but as in all our proceedings wee haue beene a Patrone of Religion and Iuſtice, (two inſeparable conſeruers of all Monarchies,) So hath all our ſtudy and care euer beene to retrench and reforme all courſes that caried any preiudice to that integritie whereat wee haue euer aymed, and as by ſo many good Lawes ſet forth in our gouernment, Iuſtice hath attained to another perfection and ſplendor, then it had in any our predeceſſors times, and with painefull and vnpleaſant buſineſſe, wee haue in the diſcipline of the Church taken away innumerable abuſes and corruptions, which it they had not beene remedied, had brought the puritie of Religion in extreame danger. Yet wee hope that none dare be ſo impudent as to affirme that by our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne power, or abſolute commandement we did the ſame (although wee enioyed our auctoritie as freely as any King or Monarch of the world) but as the diſeaſe of the Ciuill body was euer cured by the aduiſe of our three Eſtates, So the defects of the Church by the helpe and counſell of thoſe who had greateſt intereſt in them, So as the preſumpeion of our by-gone actions in our adminiſtration, whiles wee were preſent, the proofe of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly care towards this part of our Kingdome ſince our reſidence here, may be ſufficient to ſecure vs againſt all ſuch malitious calumniations. And how euer in rule of pollicie wee cannot but iudge it conuenient that two eſtates ſo inſeparably conioyned, ſhould be drawen to as great conformitie in all things as the good of both may permit; And that no Monarchy either in Ciuill or Eccleſiaſticall pollicie hath yet attained to that perfection, that it needs no reformation, or that infinite occaſions may not ariſe whereupon wiſe Princes will foreſee for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of their States, iuſt cauſe of alteration: Yet are wee and haue euer beene reſolued, not to make any ſudden or haſty change in the gouernment of that part of our Kingdome, either Ciuill or Eccleſiaſticall, but with graue aduice and conſent of our Eſtates, and the wiſeſt and beſt ſort of them whom it moſt properly concernes, much leſſe to trouble them with any vnneceſſary alteration of indifferent and Ceremoniall matters, and that vpon ſuch foreſeene aduantages, and preuention of confuſion and euill to come, as the greateſt enemies of all Peace, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Princes, and order in all gouernments ſhall not obtrude any inconuenient to the contrary. And as by Gods holy aſſiſtance, wee haue drawne that part of our Kingdome out of infinite troubles, factions, and cruell barbarities, and reduced the vttermoſt borders and confines thereof to Gods obedience, and acknowledging of our Lawes; (an Eſtate neuer heard of before, ſince this Iland hath beene inhabited) So by the ſame diuine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence and our fatherly care ouer the whole Iland, wee intend to tranſmit the ſame in good order, happy quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and flouriſhing pollicie to that poſteritie wherewith God hath bleſſed vs, and after them to the worlds end; Like as for the more verification of our Honourable intention, and to ſtop the mouthes of theſe vnquiet ſpirits, raiſers of that falſe ſcandall of alteration, We haue appointed a generall aſſembly to be holden at <hi>Dundee</hi> the laſt Tueſday of July, whereat we excepect reparation of thoſe diſorders in ſo farre as belongeth to their cenſure, and to be freed in time comming of all ſuch calumnies.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at our Honour of Hampton Court<date>the 26. day of September, in the third yeere of our Reigne of Great Britaine, France and Ireland. Anno Dom. 1605.</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Robert Barker, Printed to the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie. 1605.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
